Smith Ely Jelliffe Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Smith Ely Jelliffe Papers 1882-1977 (bulk 1885-1944)
MSS57018
Jelliffe, Smith Ely, 1866-1945
10,200 items
44 containers plus 1 oversize
18.0 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Neurologist, psychoanalyst, and educator. Correspondence, letterbooks, notebooks, genealogical material, biographical material, scrapbooks, photographs, articles, sketches, studies, newspaper clippings, memorabilia, and a diary relating primarily to Jelliffe’s career and to his family.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bleuler, Eugen, 1857-1939--Correspondence.; Brill, A. A. (Abraham Arden), 1874-1948--Correspondence.; Eitingon, M. (Max), 1880-1943--Correspondence.; Ellis, Havelock, 1859-1939--Correspondence.; Emerson, Winifred Jelliffe--Correspondence.; Federn, Paul--Correspondence.; Fenichel, Otto--Correspondence.; Ferenczi, Sándor, 1873-1933--Correspondence.; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939--Correspondence.; Goldschmidt, Helena Woodruff Jelliffe--Correspondence.; Hall, G. Stanley (Granville Stanley), 1844-1924--Correspondence.; Jelliffe family.; Jelliffe, Belinda, 1890-1979--Correspondence.; Jelliffe, Helena Dewey Leeming, -1916. Correspondence and diary.; Jelliffe, Smith Ely, 1866-1945.; Jones, Ernest, 1879-1958--Correspondence.; Jung, C. G. (Carl Gustav), 1875-1961--Correspondence.; Kraepelin, Emil, 1856-1926--Correspondence.; Laforgue, René--Correspondence.; Leeming, Joseph--Correspondence.; Leeming, Thomas Lonsdale--Correspondence.; Lewis, Nolan D. C. (Nolan Don Carpentier), 1889-1979--Correspondence.; Long, Louise Jelliffe--Correspondence.; Menninger, Karl A. (Karl Augustus), 1893-1990--Correspondence.; Meyer, Adolf, 1866-1950--Correspondence.; Rado, Sandor, 1890-1972--Correspondence.; Rank, Otto, 1884-1939--Correspondence.; Reich, Wilhelm, 1897-1957--Correspondence.; Reik, Theodor, 1888-1969--Correspondence.; Schilder, Paul, 1886-1940--Correspondence.; Stekel, Wilhelm, 1868-1940--Correspondence.; Stragnell, Sylvia Canfield Jelliffe--Correspondence.; White, William A. (William Alanson), 1870-1937--Correspondence.
Subjects
Huntington's disease.; Medicine, Psychosomatic.; Mental illness.; Neurology.; Psychiatry.; Psychoanalysis.; Psychology, Pathological.; Psychotherapy.; Schizophrenia.
Places
Alaska--Description and travel.; Europe--Description and travel.
Titles
Journal of nervous and mental disease.; Nervous and mental disease monograph series.; Psychoanalytic review.
Occupations
Educators.; Neurologists.; Psychoanalysts.
Provenance
The papers of Smith Ely Jelliffe, neurologist, psychoanalyst, and educator, were given to the Library of Congress by Arcangelo D’Amore and Nolan D. C. Lewis in 1976. Mr. and Mrs. Carel Goldschmidt deposited items in 1978, and Mrs. Goldschmidt gave additional material in 1981. The deposit was converted to a gift in 1979. Additional material was given by Robert Stragnell in 2001.
Additional Guides
Part of the Jelliffe Papers are described in The Quarterly Journal of the Library of Congress 34, no. 4 (Oct. 1977): 360-363, 374.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Smith Ely Jelliffe are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1866, Oct. 27 Born, Brooklyn, N.Y.
1888 Graduated, Brooklyn Polytechnic Institute, Brooklyn, N.Y.
1889 Ph.D., College of Physicians and Surgeons, Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1894 Married Helena (“Lelie”) Dewey Leeming (died 1916)
1896 Met William A. White
1899 Associate editor, Journal of Nervous and Mental Diseases; managing editor and owner, 1902-1945
1907 1912 Clinical professor of Mental Diseases, Fordham University, New York, N.Y.
1913 Published with William A. White, The Modern Treatment of Nervous and Mental Diseases. Philadelphia, Pa.: Lea & Febiger Founded with William A. White, Psychoanalytic Review, the first English-language publication dedicated to psychoanalysis
1915 Published with William A. White, Diseases of the Nervous System: A Text-Book of Neurology and Psychiatry. Philadelphia, Pa.: Lea & Febiger
1918 Published The Technique of Psychoanalysis. New York: Nervous and Mental Disease Publication Co., the first book devoted to analytical technique
1920 Married Belinda (“Bee”) Dobson
1928 Presided over session of July 21, third Conférence des Psychanalystes de Langue Française, Paris, France
1939 Published Sketches in Psychosomatic Medicine. New York: Nervous and Mental Disease Monographs
1945, Sept. 25 Died, Lake George, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Smith Ely Jelliffe (1866-1945) span the years 1882-1977, with the bulk dating from 1885 to 1944. The papers are organized into the following series: Correspondence, Notes, Genealogical Material, Biographical Material, Scrapbooks, Miscellany, Memorabilia, Addition, and Oversize.
Jelliffe is often credited as one of the founders of American psychosomatic medicine. He was, however, more widely known for his translations of numerous European works in neurology, psychiatry, psychopathology, and psychotherapy, and the serials he owned and edited, Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease, Psychoanalytic Review, and Nervous and Mental Disease Monograph.
The Correspondence series relates primarily to Jelliffe’s career and includes correspondents such as Eugen Bleuler, A. A. Brill, M. Eitingon, Havelock Ellis, Paul Federn, Otto Fenichel, Sándor Ferenczi, Sigmund Freud, G. Stanley Hall, Ernest Jones, C. G. Jung, Emil Kraepelin, René Laforgue, Nolan D. C. Lewis, Karl A. Menninger, Adolf Meyer, Sandor Rado, Otto Rank, Wilhelm Reich, Theodor Reik, Paul Schilder, Wilhelm Stekel, and William A. White. Also of interest is correspondence with botanists and letters received while in Germany in 1891. The letters and letterbooks are largely Jelliffe’s correspondence to and from his wife, Helena (“Lelie”) Dewey Leeming Jelliffe, daughter Helena Woodruff Jelliffe Goldschmidt, and sister Louise (“Lulu”) Jelliffe Long.
The Notes contain journals, notebooks, a study of Huntington’s chorea, lecture notes, and notes on articles concerning dementia praecox and other mental illnesses, all including many hand-drawn illustrations. Additional material related to the articles is found in the Miscellany series along with photographs, sketches by Jelliffe, and newspaper clippings.
The Genealogical Material and Biographical Material series contain notebooks of background information collected on various Jelliffe ancestors as well as autobiographical material on Jelliffe and correspondence from later years concerning genealogy. Photographs are also included in the Biographical Material.
The Scrapbooks and Memorabilia series consist of bound volumes containing correspondence, photographs, printed ephemera, newspaper clippings, and plant material. The scrapbooks relate to European trips. Also in Memorabilia are printed matter and diplomas.
The Addition contains a diary of Helena Dewey Leeming Jelliffe and a notebook of Jelliffe’s general observations. The general correspondence in the Addition was written mostly to and from family members including Jelliffe’s first wife, Helena Dewey Leeming Jelliffe; their daughters, Winifred Jelliffe Emerson, Helena Woodruff Jelliffe Goldschmidt, and Sylvia Canfield Jelliffe Stragnell; his sister Louise (“Lulu”) Jelliffe Long; brothers-in-law Thomas Lonsdale Leeming and Joseph Leeming; and second wife, Belinda (“Bee”) Jelliffe; as well as family friends. Included also is a scrapbook from a trip to Alaska in 1905 containing printed ephemera and plant material.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in nine series:
Correspondence, 1889-1944
Notes, 1886-1936
Genealogical Material, undated
Biographical Material, 1969-1977
Scrapbooks, 1890-1929
Miscellany, 1885-1937
Memorabilia, 1882-1909
Addition, 1885-1944
Oversize, 1882-1896
Container List
- Correspondence, 1889-1944 (Box 1-25)
  Letters, letterbooks, a notebook, and miscellaneous correspondence interspersed with photographs and illustrations.
  Arranged by type of material with the miscellaneous correspondence arranged alphabetically.
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - A-Bay (Box 1)
    - Bea-Bow (Box 2)
    - Bra-Ch (Box 3)
    - Cl-Cz (Box 4)
    - Da-Du (Box 5)
    - Ea-Fl (Box 6)
    - Fo-Gl (Box 7)
    - Go-Hay (Box 8)
    - He-I (Box 9)
    - Ja-Ka (Box 10)
    - Ke-Ku (Box 11)
    - La-Ly (Box 12)
    - Ma-Men (Box 13)
    - Mer-My (Box 14)
    - Na-Paz (Box 15)
    - Pe-Ri (Box 16)
    - Rob-Sch (Box 17)
    - Se-Str (Box 18)
    - Su-Vo (Box 19)
    - Wa-White, William A. (Box 20)
    - White, William A. (Box 21)
    - White, William A.-Z (Box 22)
  - Botanist letters, 1889-1892, (3 folders) (Box 23)
  - Letterbooks (Box 23)
    - Jelliffe, Smith Ely (Box 23)
      - To Helena (“Lelie”) Dewey Leeming Jelliffe (wife), pages 1-298, 1890-1891 (Box 23)
      - To Helena Dewey Leeming Jelliffe, pages 299-548, 1891-1893 (Box 24)
      - Schuendener’s Laboratory, Berlin, Germany, notebook and letters, 1891; and letters from Helena Dewey Leeming Jelliffe and Helena Woodruff Jelliffe Goldschmidt (daughter), 1908-1910 (Box 24)
    - Jelliffe, Helena Dewey Leeming ,to Jelliffe, 1890-1892, (2 folders) (Box 24)
  - Letters (Box 24)
    - Jelliffe, Smith Ely (Box 25)
      - To Helena Woodruff Jelliffe Goldschmidt and Louise (“Lulu”) Jelliffe Long (sister), 1925-1944 (Box 25)
      - With J. B. Lippincott Co. and Lea Brothers & Co., 1900-1903 (Box 25)
      - Scrapbook of letters with photographs and clippings, 1935-1943 (Box 25)
- Notes, 1886-1936 (Box 26-29)
  Notebooks, journals, articles, and a lecture.
  Arranged by type of material or title of article.
  - “Physical Signs of Dementia Praecox,” undated (Box 26)
  - Notebook (Box 26)
  - Study of Huntington’s chorea in families, undated, (2 vols.) (Box 27)
  - Journals (notes), 1901 (Box 28)
  - Botany notes, vols. I-V and IX, 1886 (Box 28)
  - “Plants of Prospect Park,” 1889 (Box 28)
  - “The Flora of Long Island,” 1890 (Box 28)
  - General, 1908 (Box 28)
  - “Priority and Progress,” vol. XLV, July 1917 (Box 29)
  - European notes, vols. I-IX, 1891 (Box 29)
  - “The Publication Way,” 1932 (Box 29)
  - “Mushroom Poisoning,” 1936 Lecture (Box 29)
  - 1906-1909, (3 vols.) (Box 29)
- Genealogical Material, undated (Box 30)
  Notebooks on Jelliffe family interspersed with photographs and correspondence.
  Arranged by volume number.
  - Jelliffe family notebook, vol. I (Box 30)
  - Jelliffe, Thomas, land transfers made by, vol. II (Box 30)
  - Taylor, Rachel Jelliffe, vol. III (Box 30)
  - Jelliffe, James, notebooks, vol. IV (Box 30)
  - Jelliffe, William, notebooks, vol. V (Box 30)
- Biographical Material, 1969-1977 (Box 31)
  Autobiographical notes and typescript, photographs, and correspondence.
  Unarranged.
  - Autobiographical notes and typescript, and photographs, undated, (2 folders) (Box 31)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1977, (2 folders) (Box 31)
- Scrapbooks, 1890-1929 (Box 31-36)
  Bound volumes containing correspondence, newspaper clippings, photographs, and printed ephemera kept by the Jelliffe family relating to European trips.
  - European trips (Box 31)
    - 1890 (Box 31)
    - 1890-1891 (Box 32)
    - 1921, 21 May-21 Oct. (vol. I) (Box 33)
    - 1924, 2 July-22 Aug. (vol. II) (Box 33)
    - 1925, Aug.-Oct. (vol. III) (Box 34)
    - 1927, Aug. (vol. IV) (Box 35)
    - 1928, June-Aug. (vol. V) (Box 35)
    - 1929, July-Aug. (vol. VI) (Box 36)
- Miscellany, 1885-1937 (Box 37)
  Family photographs, sketches by Jelliffe, articles, and newspaper clippings.
  - Photographs (Box 37)
    - Class picture, other photographs, and negatives of Jelliffe (Box 37)
    - Lake George, N.Y., vol. II, 1932-1937 (Box 37)
    - “Arcady” estate (Box 37)
    - General (Box 37)
  - Sketches by Jelliffe, 1885-1889 (Box 37)
  - Articles (Box 37)
    - “The Flora of Long Island,” 1899 (Box 37)
    - “The Vegetative Nervous System,” 1917 (Box 37)
  - Newspaper clippings and photographs (Box 37)
- Memorabilia, 1882-1909 (Box 38-42)
  Bound volumes containing newspaper clippings, photographs, plant material, printed ephemera, and correspondence.
  Arranged chronologically as received with miscellaneous items at the end.
  - Bound volumes (Box 38)
    - Vol. I, 1894-1898 (Box 38)
    - Vol. II, 1898-1906 (Box 39)
    - Vol. III, 1906-1907 (Box 40)
    - Vol. IV, 1908-1909 (Box 41)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 42)
    - Printed matter (Box 42)
    - Diplomas, 1882-1889, 1895-1896 See also Oversize (Box 42)
- Addition, 1885-1944 (Box 43-44)
  Correspondence, diary, notebook, and scrapbook.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Diary, Helena Dewey Leeming Jelliffe, 1885 (Box 43)
  - General correspondence, 1889-1894, 1920-1944, undated, (6 folders) (Box 43)
  - Miscellany, 1916-1920, undated (Box 43)
  - Notebook of general observations, 1905-1944 (Box 43)
  - Scrapbook of Alaska trip, 1905 (Box 44)
    - Bound volume (Box 44)
    - Loose items (Box 44)
- Oversize, 1882-1896 (Box OV 1)
  Diplomas.
  Arranged and described according to the series, container, and folder from which the items were removed.
  - Memorabilia (Box OV 1)
    - Diplomas, 1882-1889, 1895-1896 (Container 42) (Box OV 1)